A Guide to the Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, 1928-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland 1928-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12755
The collection consists of about 329 items. (two Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were the gift of Miss Roy Land, 1989, March 10.
Biographical/Historical Information
Selby Vernon McCasland (1896-1970), the John B. Cary Memorial Professor of Religion at the University of Virginia, was from Comanche, Texas where he attended Hardin-Simmons College (A.B. 1918) and the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary (Th.B. 1922). He was awarded the A.M. in 1924 and the Ph.D. in 1926, both from the University of Chicago. He also studied at Universities in Germany from 1926 to 1927. Prior to his arrival at the University of Virginia, he taught at Abilene Christian College, Goucher College, and the American School of Oriental Research in Jerusalem.
He married Louise Gaston in 1928 and they had two children. McCasland enjoyed great popularity among his students at the University, and he was deeply involved in University life. The YMCA in particular came under his direction periodically and benefited greatly from his enthusiasm and dedication. His academic interests included Biblical scholarship and philosophy of religion. He was a member of the Disciples of Christ Church and various learned societies. His death in 1970 came just three years after his retirement from the University faculty. He taught religion at the University of Virginia from 1939 to 1967.
Scope and Content
The Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, Professor of Religion at the University of Virginia, contain theology lectures, and information from the Young Men Christian's Association at the University of Virginia, including Board of Director correspondence, minutes, finances, insurance, notes on the history of the University of Virginia, and leases and repairs for Dawson's Row from 1920 to 1965. The correspondence includes a letter from Daniel L. Gibbes to President Colgate Darden about the YMCA sponsoring the State Wesley Foundation Conference, if it was to be held as a meeting of Christian College Students and not as an interracial meeting.
There are also notebooks containing accounts, travel notes, archaeology notes, a photo album of University of Virginia students and faculty and a scrapbook containing clippings about the Scopes trial with Clarence Darrow and William Jennings Bryan, an editorial about the trial by George Bernard Shaw, clippings about various events of the day including the gangster shootings of Angelo Genna, and a clipping about President and Mrs. Calvin Coolidge, Jr. Also in the scrapbook are programs for sermons of S. V. McCasland in 1924 and a program for the farewell address of [his father,] James Murl McCasland at Johnstown Colorado in 1925. The scrapbook has several signatures including Warren P. Blodgett, Harold H. Titua; Arthur L. Dickinson; E W Jones; W. E. Garrsion; E. M. Stunnard; Frank S. Ware; and Earl J. Sechler; and a clipping about the funeral service for University of Chicago President Ernest DeWitt Burton.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Theology lectures of Selby Vernon McCasland on Problems of Happiness and The Christian View of Sin, Grace and Salvation. 1940-1964, 6 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Included with the lectures are three programs for McCaslands' lectures for the University of Virginia Christian Association at Madison Hall and a news clipping about them.
- University of Virginia YMCA Board of Directors 1942-1964, 45 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Included are University of Virginia YMCA Board of Directors minutes, lease agreements, nominations, biographical sketches, and general information about seminars and activities. Correspondents include S. A. Mitchell, George B. Zehmer, Raymond S. Edmundson, Daniel L. Gibbes, Jr., Vincent Shea, Edward E. Younger, T. Graham Hereford, Francis H. Fife, B. F. D. Runk, Lawrence R. Quarles, Ralph W. Cherry, Donald M. McKay, the Reverend Peter Braun, S. H. O'Grince, Edward R. Slaughter, Charles E. Moran, Jr., Charles W. Smith, Marvin B. Perry, Jr., Harold Colvin, F. Rogers-Jones, and John P. MacCallum.
  There is also a letter from Daniel L. Gibbes to President Colgate Darden about the YMCA sponsoring the State Wesley Foundation Conference, if it was held as a meeting of Christian College Students and not as an interracial meeting.
- University of Virginia YMCA: #3 and #4 Dawson's Row 1955, 54 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
  There are letters, bills, receipts, and rental agreements pertaining to the YMCA properties, number three and number four Dawson's Row. Some of the correspondents are Vincent Shea, C. R. West, Mr. and Mrs. Howard Turner, Mrs. C. H. Kauffman, S. Vernon McCasland,Daniel L. Gibbes and T. Graham Hereford.
- University of Virginia YMCA Finance Committee Correspondence 1950-1958, 72 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Correspondents include University of President Colgate W. Darden, Jr., James F. Minor, Carrie B. Deane, Trust Accountant, The Peoples National Bank; Francis H. Fife, Trust Investment Officer, The Peoples National Bank; Cornelia D. Nuckols, The Peoples National Bank; Vincent Shea, Comptroller, University of Virginia YMCA; James Harry Michael, Jr.; Charles K. Woltz; Oscar B. Wooldridge, Jr., Mrs. Mary Hudson Hayward; Mr. Jay F. Waters; Richard R. Fletcher; Myron S. Miller; Jack Dalton, Mrs. Ralph Miller; Leander McCormick, George B. Zehmer, D. Clark Hyde, W. F. Souder, Wyatt C. Wood, and B. F. D. Runk.
- University of Virginia YMCA Finance Committee Documents 1942-1958, 74 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
  By-laws, financial statements and lease for Madison Hall. Included is a letter from President Colgate Darden concerning a $2500.00 annual rent for Madison Hall.
- University of Virginia YMCA Correspondence-Financial Insurance 1942-1950, 30 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Correspondents include Francis H. Fife, The Peoples National Bank; Vincent Shea, comptroller, University of Virginia YMCA; James F. Minor, Minor-Duke Mutual; W. F. Souder, Hanckel-Citizens Insurance Corporation; Wyatt C. Wood, Virginia Insurance rating Bureau; Carrie B. Deane, The Peoples National Bank; S. Vernon McCasland. The correspondence is about insurance policies for properties such as Madison Hall.
- University of Virginia YMCA - General File 1955-1957, 16 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Meeting minutes, annual report and budget information; Handwritten notes for the University Handbook; Biographical sketches of other ministers; and printed information such as a church program from the University Chapel, brochures on the University YMCA and a program for the Boy's Club Banquet.
- Notes on the History of the University YMCA n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  There are handwritten notes on the plans and history of the University of Virginia YMCA including proposed by-laws.
- University of Virginia YMCA Program Committee Records 1964-1965, 3 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
- University of Virginia YMCA Property Committee Correspondence 1964-1965, 4 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
- University of Virginia YMCA - Contact with Oscar B. Woodridge, Jr. 1946-1949, 5 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
- YMCA - Printed Matter n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Scrapbook 1920-1925, 1 item. (Box 2)
  News clippings about Clarence Darrow and William Jennings Bryan during the Scopes evolution trial; editorial by George Bernard Shaw about the trial; Programs for sermons of Evangelist S. V. McCasland ,1924 and program for the farewell address of James Murl McCasland at Johnstown Colorado 1925; More news clippings and articlesle about President and Mrs. Coolidge; article about gangster shooting of Angelo Genna; Several signatures including Warren P. Blodgett, Harold H. Titua; Arthur L. Dickinson; E W Jones; W. E. Garrsion; E. M. Stunnard; Frank S. Ware; and Earl J. Sechler; and a news clipping about the funeral service for University of Chicago President Ernest DeWitt Burton.
- Grade Book [Goucher College] 1928, 1 item. (Box 2)
- Article titled, Crediting Bible Study in the Schools by W. M. Forrest from the Normal Bulletin n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
- Journal of accounts, expenses and family history 1929, 1 item. (Box 2)
- Journal with notes on archaeology 1937-1939, 1 item. (Box 2)
- Journal with notes on travels 1939, 1 item. (Box 2)
- Photo Album n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
- German Notebook n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)